<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:25:31 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>custom debian installation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:25:31 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like btrfs. One of the main reasons I choose btrfs as a filesystem is for backup tools like snapper and timeshift. With these tools, your system is much more resilient to breaking on you since you can simply roll back to a previous snapshot! Besides the snapshots, I like the compression, the CoW filesystem, the list goes on. Unfortunately when it comes to installations, most distros make it a little frustrating to get the setup &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how I want it. Not impossible but frustrating. While I love NixOS for it&amp;rsquo;s immutability, IaC approach, and stability, I also love Debian. It&amp;rsquo;s ole reliable in my eyes. The granddaddy of Linux distros. It&amp;rsquo;s your favorite Linux distribution&amp;rsquo;s favorite Linux distribution. For that reason, I wanted to document the process it takes to get my preferred setup which includes:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like btrfs. One of the main reasons I choose btrfs as a filesystem is for backup tools like snapper and timeshift. With these tools, your system is much more resilient to breaking on you since you can simply roll back to a previous snapshot! Besides the snapshots, I like the compression, the CoW filesystem, the list goes on. Unfortunately when it comes to installations, most distros make it a little frustrating to get the setup &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how I want it. Not impossible but frustrating. While I love NixOS for it&amp;rsquo;s immutability, IaC approach, and stability, I also love Debian. It&amp;rsquo;s ole reliable in my eyes. The granddaddy of Linux distros. It&amp;rsquo;s your favorite Linux distribution&amp;rsquo;s favorite Linux distribution. For that reason, I wanted to document the process it takes to get my preferred setup which includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UEFI boot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separate boot partition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passphrase encrypted LUKs container with BTRFS as filesystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separate subvols for:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/var/log&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/snapshots
It should be noted that this is my preferred installation for a desktop installation or if I was running Debian bare-metal. If it were a bare metal server I might try to configure a device for unencrypting the drive at boot for unattended reboots. I tend to not care &lt;em&gt;as much&lt;/em&gt; about encryption on servers that are housed behind physical access controls. I personally think that encryption is an absolute necessity for laptops, and as a side note I think it&amp;rsquo;s criminal for Microsoft to not allow for encryption on Windows Home versions. For VMs, I keep things a little simpler and make the host filesystem btrfs and the VM gets EXT4. If you&amp;rsquo;re curious on that, I wrote a blog post on it for the hackerspace I&amp;rsquo;m trying to get running &lt;a href=&#34;https://sodakhacker.space/projects/vm-template/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll boot into Debian stable and go with &amp;lsquo;Advanced Options&amp;rsquo; -&amp;gt; &amp;lsquo;Expert Graphical Install&amp;rsquo;. Then we&amp;rsquo;ll walk through that, setting the language and keyboard layout. Once we hit the &amp;lsquo;Load Installer components from installation media&amp;rsquo; we&amp;rsquo;ll hit quite a few of these components. To be honest, we probably don&amp;rsquo;t need all of these, but we&amp;rsquo;ll just add some additional ones to be safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/components.png&#34; alt=&#34;components&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the main menu, we&amp;rsquo;ll detect the network devices and configure that to whatever our network setup is. We&amp;rsquo;ll select a mirror of the Debian archive, I recommend whatever is physically closest to you, and setup users and passwords as needed. After clock configuration, we move into the disk detection and setup. This is where the magic happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;disk-partitioning&#34;&gt;disk partitioning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we select &amp;lsquo;Manual&amp;rsquo; under disk partition and configure a new partition table in &lt;code&gt;gpt&lt;/code&gt; by selecting our disk we want to install Debian on. Once we have the partition table setup, we select the free space and create a 512MB partition for EFI and configure it as such:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/efi-part.png&#34; alt=&#34;efi-part&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that we create a 2GB partition, format it as EXT4 and mount it at &lt;code&gt;/boot&lt;/code&gt;. Again we select the &lt;code&gt;FREE SPACE&lt;/code&gt; to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/boot-part.png&#34; alt=&#34;boot-part&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, we move into our LUKS partition. We select &amp;lsquo;Configure encrypted volumes&amp;rsquo; at the top of the menu. Confirm writing the partitions we have configured so far. Then select &amp;lsquo;Create encrypted volumes&amp;rsquo; and select the free space on our drive. Give it a name, and choose to erase the data or not. It may take a while but it is best practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/btrfs-crypt.png&#34; alt=&#34;btrfs-crypt&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that write the changes and configure the encrypted volumes. From the main encryption drive menu select &amp;lsquo;Finish&amp;rsquo;. This will prompt for a passphrase on the partition. Once this is finished, we get dumped back at the main disk partition menu. We now have an additional option at the top of our partition menu that allows us to configure the unlocked LUKS container. We&amp;rsquo;ll need to configure that for btrfs by selecting the new entry and mount it at root. We&amp;rsquo;ll select the &amp;lsquo;Finish partitioning and write changes to disk&amp;rsquo; option at the very bottom and then move into the console. Your partitions should look something like this before selecting &amp;lsquo;Finish partitioning and write changes to disk&amp;rsquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/post-crypt.png&#34; alt=&#34;post-crypt&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll get an error stating that there&amp;rsquo;s no swap partition. You can either add one within the LUKS container or you can configure zswap or have no swap. That&amp;rsquo;s up to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note, if you didn&amp;rsquo;t select expert install the installer will automatically install the base system. This isn&amp;rsquo;t ideal because we haven&amp;rsquo;t configured the subvols yet.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-the-shell&#34;&gt;enter the shell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we move into a console by hitting &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Fn+Alt F2&lt;/code&gt;. This will dump us into a busybox shell. We can see where things are mounted with &lt;code&gt;df -h&lt;/code&gt;. We can see that currently our btrfs partition is mounted at &lt;code&gt;/target&lt;/code&gt;. However, this is actually the root subvol mounted. We need to unmount &lt;code&gt;/target&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;/target/boot&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;/target/boot/efi&lt;/code&gt; to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/initial-disk-busybox.png&#34; alt=&#34;init-disk-busybox&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;umount /target/boot/efi
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;umount /target/boot
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;umount /target
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now we mount the unlocked luks container partition with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount /dev/mapper/sda3_crypt /target
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;cd /target
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can see the root subvol given the name &lt;code&gt;@rootfs&lt;/code&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll just change that to &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; and create our new subvols:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mv @rootfs @
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;btrfs subvol create @home
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;btrfs subvol create @snapshots
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;btrfs subvol create @var_log
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;With our subvols created, we can remount our root subvol, create proper directories to mount the additional subvols, and remount our boot and efi partitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;umount /target
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount -o noatime,space_cache&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;v2,compress&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;zstd,ssd,discard&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;async,subvol&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;@ /dev/mapper/sda3_crypt /target
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mkdir -p /target/home /target/var/log /target/snapshots
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount -o noatime,space_cache&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;v2,compress&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;zstd,ssd,discard&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;async,subvol&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;@home /dev/mapper/sda3_crypt /target/home
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount -o noatime,space_cache&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;v2,compress&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;zstd,ssd,discard&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;async,subvol&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;@snapshots /dev/mapper/sda3_crypt /target/snapshots
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount -o noatime,space_cache&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;v2,compress&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;zstd,ssd,discard&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;async,subvol&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;@var_log /dev/mapper/sda3_crypt /target/var/log
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount /dev/sda2 /target/boot
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mount /dev/sda1 /target/boot/efi
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After mounting all the subvols and partitions, your output of &lt;code&gt;df -h&lt;/code&gt; should look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/mounts.png&#34; alt=&#34;mounts&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once that&amp;rsquo;s been verified we can move into modifying &lt;code&gt;/target/etc/fstab&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;nano&lt;/code&gt;. We can copy lines with &lt;code&gt;Alt + 6&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + U&lt;/code&gt;. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to add the mount options to take advantage of some of the features of btrfs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/custom-debian-install/fstab.png&#34; alt=&#34;fstab&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you&amp;rsquo;re curious on what each mount option does:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;noatime&lt;/code&gt; - This option doesn&amp;rsquo;t update the last accessed time on a file when it&amp;rsquo;s read. Doing that creates a write on the file and isn&amp;rsquo;t needed on SSDs or NVME drives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;space_cache=v2&lt;/code&gt; - Sets the space cache (which is how btrfs knows what parts of the disk are free) to be version 2, the more modern option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;compress=zstd&lt;/code&gt; - Sets compression algorithm to &lt;code&gt;zstd&lt;/code&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a good compression algorithm that doesn&amp;rsquo;t take a lot of CPU overhead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssd&lt;/code&gt; - Sets btrfs to behave in a way best suited for ssds. Technically it should detect this by default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;discard=async&lt;/code&gt; - Sets TRIM (the operation of erasing storage blocks) to be async allowing those operations to be pooled and performed in the background. If not set properly can lead to weird system pauses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;subvol=@&lt;/code&gt; - Mounts the appropriate subvolume in the right location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Double check that these entries are correct - otherwise you won&amp;rsquo;t have a bootable system. Once that&amp;rsquo;s done, we can move back to the gui installer and install the base system with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Fn+Alt F5&lt;/code&gt;. At this point, the hard part is over. I select the defaults for the kernel installation generic kernel module stuff. Once that step is done, you can continue to install a DE if you&amp;rsquo;d like. And that&amp;rsquo;s it! Boot into your system and enjoy an encrypted btrfs Debian system!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the sodak hackerspace</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro_to_hackerspace/intro_to_hackerspace/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:24:08 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/intro_to_hackerspace/intro_to_hackerspace/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My HomeLab has been the biggest boon to my career in IT. It provided me a space to deploy, manage, and experiment with different technologies and also reduce my reliance on big tech companies by self hosting my own services. It&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of fun to build, deploy, break, upgrade, and learn in my own little kingdom so to speak. A while back I was listening to a podcast, I believe it was &lt;a href=&#34;https://linuxunplugged.com/&#34;&gt;Linux Unplugged&lt;/a&gt; and one of the hosts mentioned that they visited a hackerspace in Berlin. The name alone was enticing but to hear them describe this enclave of technology enthusiasts that meets up and works on projects, learn from each other and have a space to nerd out over things sounded incredible and made me wonder if I could pull something like that off in my own community.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My HomeLab has been the biggest boon to my career in IT. It provided me a space to deploy, manage, and experiment with different technologies and also reduce my reliance on big tech companies by self hosting my own services. It&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of fun to build, deploy, break, upgrade, and learn in my own little kingdom so to speak. A while back I was listening to a podcast, I believe it was &lt;a href=&#34;https://linuxunplugged.com/&#34;&gt;Linux Unplugged&lt;/a&gt; and one of the hosts mentioned that they visited a hackerspace in Berlin. The name alone was enticing but to hear them describe this enclave of technology enthusiasts that meets up and works on projects, learn from each other and have a space to nerd out over things sounded incredible and made me wonder if I could pull something like that off in my own community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;goals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s few ideas that I had going into this endeavour. The first was to provide a space to learn, tinker, and collaborate on projects surrounding the computer space. That&amp;rsquo;s simple enough, people could bring their own workstations and work on their own infra with help from others as needed. But it&amp;rsquo;d be fun to have some shared infrastructure - a community HomeLab if you will. As I thought about the idea of shared infrastructure there would be levels of logistical organization that would need to be in place, especially if we had a server or two or three that people could hop on. While shared user accounts and just handing out root credentials is easy it&amp;rsquo;s also terrifying and stupid. The only thing is that managing an organization is difficult, complex, and expensive and while the first two will always be the case, I could work hard to make the cost low. Like really low. Then the idea struck:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An entire organization built on top of open source for management and infrastructure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built on top of Proxmox, the idea for now as a PoC is to have an all in one management box that you only need to plug into a WAN port on a modem. The entire rest of the infrastructure will be virtualized. Opnsense or Pfsense for the router, headscale for the VPN, FreeIPA for Identity Management, self hosted SSO, Wazuh for SIEM and XDR, managed by ansible, almost everything an organization needs to get off the ground and all while minimizing the reliance on big tech companies. Eventually if it takes off, a template box could be created and shipped to members and everyone could host a node independently and integrate with services as needed (so long as the network connection via headscale is enough).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, as often happens, life has been crazy and my free time went from minimal to zero for quite some time. The idea was always still there though and eventually the opportunity presented itself to launch the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sodakhacker.space/&#34;&gt;SoDak Hackerspace&lt;/a&gt;. The domain was bought, the initial hardware was gathered together, Proxmox installed, and then &amp;hellip; that opportunity fell through. But the dream persisted and progress has happened recently. I write all this to say that I hope one day the SoDak Hackerspace will really start to come together and I get people within my local community involved in it and meetups start happening with projects to work on. If you visit the hackerspace site today, there&amp;rsquo;s not much. Just my profile and I think an initial blog post about the laptop I had started to make into the primary Proxmox node. I did hit a stroke of luck and acquired much better hardware to start with than the laptop so in that sense, we&amp;rsquo;re doing pretty well. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to post on the hackerspace blog more often as it gets off the ground starting with a little more detailed writeup of the initial setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently Proxmox has been installed, headscale has been configured and working, and there&amp;rsquo;s a pfsense box that has been configured for the internal infrastructure as well a DMZ if deemed necessary. We also have a public xonotic server that can be a bit latent to be honest. My next step is to configure some server templates, get Ansible stood up, and install FreeIPA on a box or two as a way to have identity management. I figured the earlier that gets setup the better so accounts can be created and managed in there. If anybody sees this and has an interest in it feel free to email me at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:alex@sodakhacker.space&#34;&gt;alex@sodakhacker.space&lt;/a&gt; or take a look at the website &lt;a href=&#34;https://sodakhacker.space&#34;&gt;https://sodakhacker.space&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>asm101</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/asm101/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 21:21:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/asm101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently self-evaluated my skills in the offensive security space and while it was a little uncomfortable to confront my own deficiencies, it was a good first step in remediating those gaps in my knowledge. While I won&amp;rsquo;t reveal all the results here, I will say that I noticed there was a lack of low level programming knowledge. Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been self-taught for the vast majority of my career I never had to slog through any courses involving lower level languages. All the programming I&amp;rsquo;ve done has really been scripting in Python and PowerShell because that&amp;rsquo;s what my jobs necessitated and there were many other things to learn in the offensive security space. This gap seemed like a good place to start in my journey to improve my skillset. There&amp;rsquo;s tons of resources out there for low level programming and I was happy to find that TCM recently launched an &lt;a href=&#34;https://academy.tcm-sec.com/p/assembly-101&#34;&gt;Assembly 101&lt;/a&gt; course in their academy. Having Just taken the PJPT from TCM, about which you can read my experience &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/pjpt/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I figured why not spend the $30 for a month and see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently self-evaluated my skills in the offensive security space and while it was a little uncomfortable to confront my own deficiencies, it was a good first step in remediating those gaps in my knowledge. While I won&amp;rsquo;t reveal all the results here, I will say that I noticed there was a lack of low level programming knowledge. Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been self-taught for the vast majority of my career I never had to slog through any courses involving lower level languages. All the programming I&amp;rsquo;ve done has really been scripting in Python and PowerShell because that&amp;rsquo;s what my jobs necessitated and there were many other things to learn in the offensive security space. This gap seemed like a good place to start in my journey to improve my skillset. There&amp;rsquo;s tons of resources out there for low level programming and I was happy to find that TCM recently launched an &lt;a href=&#34;https://academy.tcm-sec.com/p/assembly-101&#34;&gt;Assembly 101&lt;/a&gt; course in their academy. Having Just taken the PJPT from TCM, about which you can read my experience &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/pjpt/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I figured why not spend the $30 for a month and see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-basics&#34;&gt;the basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic knowledge I had been at least exposed to if not studied outright. Things like hex values, binary, translating values, etc. was nothing new to me, but I appreciated the refresher. The lessons on how a processor actually works was something I had heard about before as well but never really sat down and really digested. I thought those videos were well done and ended up getting a good basic idea of how a simple CPU uses logic gates and perform operations based on circuits built from the logic gates. Everyone knows that computers only use 1s and 0s, but seeing that explanation at an in-depth level was very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning about the Control Unit, the Arithmetic Logic Unit (ALU), and of course the registers and how they all worked in conjunction with the ROM (not sure if that&amp;rsquo;s true for modern CPUS, but this was in the example given for the intro section) really helped to create a more holistic view of the processor. Keeping that in mind as I worked my way through the course, it was cool to visualize how everything flowed from the assembly instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-with-the-8086-emulator---16-bit-processor&#34;&gt;running with the 8086 emulator - 16 bit processor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://yjdoc2.github.io/8086-emulator-web/&#34;&gt;8086 emulator&lt;/a&gt; allowed for a simpler way of getting hands on keyboard compared to x64 assembly. The emulator also gave a more detailed view of registry and memory values which was &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; helpful as a beginner. Overall I think having this section was one of the best parts of the course. I felt that each video was a good length allowing for me to easily get through one or two whenever I had the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;note&lt;/strong&gt;: The course used a self hosted docker container for the emulator. I linked to the web version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/asm101/8086_emulator.png&#34; alt=&#34;8086 Web Emulator&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-challenges-16-bit&#34;&gt;code challenges 16-bit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code challenges were great. Some of them I was able to get in a short amount of time while others needed multiple hours and breaks. There was one that I was unable to complete on my own, the &lt;code&gt;lods&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;stods&lt;/code&gt; number addition challenge, but I never felt completely lost on any of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point I wrote a program that met all the requirements of the challenge but looking at the instructor&amp;rsquo;s code I noticed that he kept everything in the registers while I moved things into RAM. It was an interesting learning moment where I asked myself what&amp;rsquo;s the benefit of keeping all the data in registers. After thinking for a little while I had a neat realization: keeping everything in registers radically improves the speed of the instructions compared to the overhead of moving it into RAM. The registers have the advantage of being located inside the CPU while grabbing data from RAM requires additional operations. Something you don&amp;rsquo;t really think about using high-level languages that I&amp;rsquo;m used to. Below is a simple example of 8086 code.&lt;/p&gt;



  &lt;div class=&#34;collapsable-code&#34;&gt;
    &lt;input id=&#34;1&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;  /&gt;
    &lt;label for=&#34;1&#34;&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;collapsable-code__language&#34;&gt;nasm&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;collapsable-code__title&#34;&gt;16 bit assembly snippet&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&#34;collapsable-code__toggle&#34; data-label-expand=&#34;Show&#34; data-label-collapse=&#34;Hide&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;pre class=&#34;language-nasm&#34; &gt;&lt;code&gt;
;Program to store string &amp;#34;Don&amp;#39;t Print This. Print This.&amp;#34; starting at 0x20000
; and then print out only the &amp;#34;Print This.&amp;#34; Portion of the string.
set 0x2000 ;setting start of data directive
string: db &amp;#34;Don&amp;#39;t Print This. Print This.&amp;#34; ; Store the string
start:
mov AH, 0x13 ; Setting up AH for int 0x10 subfunction 0x13
mov CX, 0x0b ; Setting up CX for number of chars in string - 11chars
mov BX, 0x2000 ; Set memory address for mov into ES
mov ES, BX ; set ES for string print
mov BP, 0x12; set base pointer to string offset - effectively eliminating the first part of the string
int 0x10 ; call to printchars
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;moving-to-x64&#34;&gt;moving to x64&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was definitely a jump in difficulty here, and in the beginning going from the emulator to just raw assembly and all the new syntax, tools, and commands was a little overwhelming but I don&amp;rsquo;t know how I would change anything to be honest. Maybe discussing 32 bit for a small section would help, but it could also just add unnecessary material. I did re-watch many of the videos for this section, and sought out a couple of additional videos on beginning with x64 assembly. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I did that because at least one of the videos I watched used &lt;code&gt;nasm&lt;/code&gt;, and like Andrew says in his TCM videos, the syntax is slightly different and a little closer to the 8086 emulator syntax. One thing I had going for me was plenty of Linux experience so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t afraid of the CLI and I really liked the &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt; tui interface. That&amp;rsquo;s something that I&amp;rsquo;ll be keeping in my back pocket for future debugging or playing around in assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I think part of the increased difficulty has to do with the &lt;strong&gt;System V Application Binary Interface (ABI)&lt;/strong&gt; and the increased responsibility to manage the size and content of the registers. Having arguments in registers instead of pushing to the stack adds complexity. The concept of &lt;strong&gt;callee-saved registers&lt;/strong&gt; took a bit to wrap my head around and made me think more about what values were going to remain after calling a function and which ones I needed to preserve manually. Having all the additional space in registers also makes it a little tougher to view the contents of the lower registers, at least within &lt;code&gt;gdb&lt;/code&gt; vs. the emulator. These challenges will likely work themselves out with more practice and just wrestling with the material, but they were and are things that I personally struggle with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/posts/asm101/gdb.png&#34; alt=&#34;gdb tui&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-challenges-x64&#34;&gt;code challenges x64&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were a struggle. It was the first time in the course where I felt pretty lost. As mentioned above I rewatched the section videos and it took a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time to put the pieces together. I finally got the skeletal structure of the first challenge but couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite put the pieces together. What I found challenging about it was the memory alignment and staying compliant with ABI. Eventually I spent so much time that I had to look at Andrew&amp;rsquo;s code. Luckily about 90% of it made total sense. It was the fine details of restoring register values after the function call and some of the base pointer alignment stuff that still left me a little lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did get significantly farther with the TCM coding challenge. Admittedly I did use AI to help my understanding of what I was doing and validate my understanding. It didn&amp;rsquo;t write any of the code, just checked my own work. I find that&amp;rsquo;s the best use for AI in these types of situations. I got hung up on the bonus longer than I should have and eventually I spent too much time and needed to move forward due to time constraints. As for the last challenge, I&amp;rsquo;ll leave that to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-section---memory-safety&#34;&gt;final section - memory safety&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was actually the most fun I had in the entire course. It was also the most difficult, but applying everything I learned over the entire course to start performing exploits was really satisfying. At the beginning of my journey into computer science and IT work, I looked at some low level programming and exploitation material but it flew way over my head at the time. The way the material was presented in this course was great and actually seemed to wake up some of the concepts I had seen a long time ago. I walked away from the course with a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; better understanding of things like nopsleds, avoiding bad characters in shellcode, and stack smashing attacks in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final challenge was really a challenge related to writing shellcode. My struggles continued and after spending a fair amount of time on it (4 hours over the course of a few days), I decided to grab the shellcode and run from there. Interestingly enough, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get it work on my host machine running NixOS (I could get a shell but not run commands, I think it had something to do with the path and nix store?), but I did get it to run in an Ubuntu virtual machine. Overall listening to the explanation of the shellcode was really useful and I see the train of though as far as deciding on the syscall needed and getting that setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-impressions&#34;&gt;overall impressions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal in taking this course was to start to gain a better understanding of programming at a low-level and more specifically how to take advantage of that as an offensive security professional. I would say that this course far exceeded my expectation in doing that and gave me a solid foundation to build on moving forward. I thought the best section was the memory safety section and the &amp;lsquo;weakest&amp;rsquo; one was the x86-64 functions section, but really the material was all good. At this point for me it&amp;rsquo;s about continuing to practice with assembly and low-level programming. At the end of the course Andrew mentioned if anybody would like to see another course from him. It&amp;rsquo;d be great to see him teach a course on C. I would take that course in a heartbeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking about assembly really has me curious about different CPU architectures and how efficient each one is at handling instructions. It&amp;rsquo;s my understanding that ARM and RISC-V have a better or more efficient instruction set and that&amp;rsquo;s part of what leads to the increased battery life on machines with that architecture. I&amp;rsquo;d like to dig a little into either or both of those assembly languages at some point to see how it differs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very beginning of my IT studies I did come across a book that went into low-level programming, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Hacking-Art-Exploitation-Jon-Erickson/dp/1593271441&#34;&gt;Hacking: The Art of Exploitation&lt;/a&gt; by Jon Erickson, and while I did manage to read the book I didn&amp;rsquo;t grasp most of the concepts. I took the book as a challenge to conquer and not material to really understand. The truth is that I just didn&amp;rsquo;t have the knowledge that I do now. I would like to try and read this book again with the assembly knowledge that I have now and see how much more it makes sense to me now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option I&amp;rsquo;ve been seriously looking at is &lt;a href=&#34;https://learncodethehardway.org/c/&#34;&gt;Learn C the Hard Way&lt;/a&gt;. I completed Learn Python the Hard Way years ago and found it to be helpful. One of the reasons this course sticks out to me is the focus put on defensive programming and the mention of getting to exploit C code during the course. s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;additional-resources&#34;&gt;additional resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/6S5KRJv-7RU?si=vhRtkYRD41yiBFRG&#34;&gt;Low Level YouTube Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/VQAKkuLL31g?si=hXH3DnUysen19RFc&#34;&gt;kupala Assembly Tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pjpt</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/pjpt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 21:13:47 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/pjpt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I focused on acquiring my 1st Offensive security certification. I chose the PJPT (Practical Junior Penetration Tester) because I had taken some training from TCM a while back and thought it was good material, and the cost was easy to justify. I managed to get the certification the second attempt (more on that later). Overall found the experience to be a good one, and recommend it for beginners. I really like the hands on keyboard style of examination and found this to be a great entry level exam for someone like myself who&amp;rsquo;s done some amount of network penetration testing, but wanted to take a low stakes level exam to get used to the format and the formal report writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year I focused on acquiring my 1st Offensive security certification. I chose the PJPT (Practical Junior Penetration Tester) because I had taken some training from TCM a while back and thought it was good material, and the cost was easy to justify. I managed to get the certification the second attempt (more on that later). Overall found the experience to be a good one, and recommend it for beginners. I really like the hands on keyboard style of examination and found this to be a great entry level exam for someone like myself who&amp;rsquo;s done some amount of network penetration testing, but wanted to take a low stakes level exam to get used to the format and the formal report writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;training&#34;&gt;training&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PEH (Practical Ethical Hacking) course was a really good penetration testing Active Directory basics course. I actually took an earlier version of the course through Udemy years ago, and found some things to be the same, but many parts were updated as they should have been. If you go on the TCM discord( which I did infrequently, but did from time to time), you&amp;rsquo;ll often hear that the PEH is all you&amp;rsquo;ll need to pass the PJPT. That is an entirely accurate statement from my experience. My one gripe with the training was the report writing section. I felt that it was lacking in the necessary information to actually write a report that would allow you to pass the PJPT in the 1st attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;exam-experience&#34;&gt;exam experience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took my exam on a Thursday to start so I&amp;rsquo;d be done with the exam by Monday. You&amp;rsquo;re given 2 days with machines, and two days to write the report &amp;amp; submit for grading. I found the lab environment to be quite stable, and only really having to reset for a minor issue once, which was cleared up right way. I went into the exam with a methodology ready and used an obsidian vault to take my notes. I followed my methodology which led me to domain compromise within about 8 hours. I think I could have got DA quicker, but I was treating this like a real engagement and trying to find all the possible vulnerabilities and exploit them. Honestly I had fun during my time in the actual environment and I liked that you could use any tools you wanted to bring. I had taken a Red Team training through my work before this exam and played with some really nice tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Raikia/CredNinja&#34;&gt;CredNinja&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/c3c/ADExplorerSnapshot.py&#34;&gt;ADExplorerSnapshot.py&lt;/a&gt;, and the Windows-based offensive security box &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mandiant/commando-vm&#34;&gt;CommandoVM&lt;/a&gt; and liked that I could bring whatever I wanted to the exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;report-writing&#34;&gt;report writing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the pain point. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s my inexperience in writing formal reports, maybe it&amp;rsquo;s TCM&amp;rsquo;s training, maybe its the report template TCM provides. whatever it was, it took me 2 days to do it. Admittedly I made a silly mistake in my first submission, but when I asked for clarification for my 2nd submission I did not get any clarity on what exactly I should include. So I took my time and threw in everything that I had. So. Many. Screenshots. About halfway through, I thought to myself there&amp;rsquo;s got to be a way to automate this process. If-had to do this frequently I&amp;rsquo;d probably try to template it out in Obsidian, or work on some other &amp;lsquo;markdown automation. The report writing and submission was not fun, but a tedious slog. I guess that&amp;rsquo;s the price you pay for getting to do really cool work. Once I finished the second writeup, I was proud of all the work and information I put into the report and was happy to have it graded in ~5 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 21:03:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been studying various technologies since 2018 primarily through my HomeLab and various online Cyber Training platforms like HackTheBox and TryHackMe. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working in IT professionally since May of 2021 getting my first job as a Junior Linux System Administrator. After two years in that position I transitioned into a SOC Analyst Role, and in February of 2025 moved into an Offensive Security Engineering position. This blog is I believe the third iteration of its kind. From Hugo to Ghost to Hugo again. Thanks for stopping by and I hope you find something informative here!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been studying various technologies since 2018 primarily through my HomeLab and various online Cyber Training platforms like HackTheBox and TryHackMe. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working in IT professionally since May of 2021 getting my first job as a Junior Linux System Administrator. After two years in that position I transitioned into a SOC Analyst Role, and in February of 2025 moved into an Offensive Security Engineering position. This blog is I believe the third iteration of its kind. From Hugo to Ghost to Hugo again. Thanks for stopping by and I hope you find something informative here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;experience&#34;&gt;experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network Penetration Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Application Penetration Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proficiency in Linux systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scripting in Python and PowerShell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infrastructure deployment and management through Ansible and Terraform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version Control through Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application deployment and management through Docker utilizing Docker Compose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtualization through Proxmox (KVM), ESXi, and VMWare Workstation Pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-projects&#34;&gt;personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-hosted Cyber Range through &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ludus.cloud/&#34;&gt;ludus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IaC version controlled HomeLab utilizing &lt;a href=&#34;https://nixos.org/&#34;&gt;NixOS&lt;/a&gt; publicly hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mcculleytech/nixos-config&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secrets Management through &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Mic92/sops-nix&#34;&gt;SOPS Nix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Servers deployed with &lt;a href=&#34;https://grahamc.com/blog/erase-your-darlings/&#34;&gt;impermanance&lt;/a&gt;, rebuilding the systems at boot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mesh VPN Configured with Tailscale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub Action for automating package updates to repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning Terraform and AWS, DigitalOcean deployments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malware Development through &lt;a href=&#34;https://maldevacademy.com/&#34;&gt;Maldev Academy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self Hosted LLM through ollama and OpenWebUI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version Controlled Hugo Website via GitHub (The site you&amp;rsquo;re on now!).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub Action for AutoDeployment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;certifications&#34;&gt;certifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;a688c239-9846-49e6-9df5-353c49057516&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;8ad94de6-a6a5-4c34-a805-f5e6b777d5a9&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;6f85471e-0857-418e-8897-5d9630b47570&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;685b5d33-b59b-43b9-a087-20990fc52128&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;b2622dc2-452a-4579-a5db-d9baa52c4228&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;8b9e3bf7-2c03-4f0f-bb4e-996cf48a529f&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;88be3e32-dc52-4c65-9820-e24977bd85a5&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-iframe-width=&#34;150&#34; data-iframe-height=&#34;270&#34; data-share-badge-id=&#34;88dab31a-431a-4e86-ac2e-c1aae23c5f4e&#34; data-share-badge-host=&#34;https://www.credly.com&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; async src=&#34;//cdn.credly.com/assets/utilities/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;display:flex; gap:1rem; align-items:center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://api.accredible.com/v1/frontend/credential_website_embed_image/badge/127337054&#34; width=&#34;150&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://eu.api.accredible.com/v1/frontend/credential_website_embed_image/badge/15559937&#34; width=&#34;150&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;trainings&#34;&gt;trainings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mandiant Creative Red Team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mandiant Azure Penetration Testing Basics (Custom training)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mandiant Essentials of Malware Analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCM Practical Ethical Hacker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCM C# For Hackers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCM Assembly 101&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCM Python 201 For Hackers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HackTheBox Active Directory Penetration Tester Path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
